<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-23T15:58:32+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pieter-Jan</title><subtitle>Systematic trading and data science things.
</subtitle><author><name>GitHub User</name><email>your-email@domain.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">The Low Volatility Factor: A Boring Way to Make Money?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/quant/2024/12/15/low-volatility-factor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Low Volatility Factor: A Boring Way to Make Money?" /><published>2024-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/quant/2024/12/15/low-volatility-factor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/quant/2024/12/15/low-volatility-factor.html"><![CDATA[<p>The <strong>low-volatility factor</strong> is a well-known and widely researched concept in factor investing. Simply put, it focuses on selecting stocks with smaller price swings. These more stable, often “boring” stocks tend to outperform their more volatile counterparts on a <strong>risk-adjusted</strong> basis. Now, you might be thinking—doesn’t higher risk always mean higher returns? Well, as with most things in life, not always. In this post, I’ll take a look at whether the conventional belief about risk and return still holds true.</p>

<p>I’ll show you how to construct a <strong>simple long-short portfolio</strong> using the low-volatility factor, drawing on the <strong>Russell 1000 universe</strong>. I’ll also explain how <strong>volatility targeting</strong> can further enhance your strategy’s performance.</p>

<h3 id="tradable-universe"><strong>Tradable Universe</strong></h3>

<p>Let’s start by defining our tradable universe. For this, I’m using the <strong>Russell 1000</strong> index, which includes the largest 1000 companies in the U.S. Over time, I’ve excluded stocks trading below $5. The analysis spans from <strong>1995 to 2024</strong>, and I’ve visualized the number of tradable stocks during this period, which hovers around 1000. It’s also worth mentioning that we have over <strong>3,300 different stocks</strong> in our universe, as stocks enter and exit over time. Most importantly, these are the <strong>point-in-time constituents</strong>, which help to avoid <strong>survivorship bias</strong>. I plotted the number of tradable stocks in Figure 1, which naturally fluctuates around 1000.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/2024-12-15-low-volatility-factor/nr_stocks.svg" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1</strong>: Number of tradable stocks over time.</p>

<h3 id="defining-the-low-volatility-factor"><strong>Defining the Low Volatility Factor</strong></h3>

<p>The <strong>low-volatility factor</strong> targets stocks that have historically demonstrated lower price fluctuations. To identify these stocks, I calculated volatility over three different time windows:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>5-day volatility</strong></li>
  <li><strong>10-day volatility</strong></li>
  <li><strong>21-day volatility</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>I use multiple time windows for a simple reason—it just works better. This combined approach smooths out short-term noise and provides a more robust measure of volatility. The average volatility across these timeframes is 33%, with the first quartile at 18%, the third quartile at 39%, and a median of 26%. I winsorized the data, capping the lower bound at 5% and the upper bound at 200%, which explains the small bump at the right tail of the distribution.</p>

<p>Below, you can see the distribution of annualized volatilities across over <strong>3,300 stocks</strong> throughout the entire sample period. This distribution is positively skewed, resembling a <strong>log-normal</strong> pattern—most stocks have moderate volatility, but a smaller number exhibit high volatility.</p>

<p>The distribution of volatilities shows a <strong>positively skewed</strong> pattern, resembling a <strong>log-normal</strong> distribution. This suggests that while most stocks have volatilities between 18% and 39%, a smaller number of stocks exhibit high volatility.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/2024-12-15-low-volatility-factor/distribution_volatilities.svg" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 2</strong>: Histogram showing the distribution of volatility across the tradable universe.</p>

<p>As a first check, I computed the correlation with the raw annualized volatility and forward return and Sharpe ratio for the next 10 days. Interestingly, when using Pearson correlation, we find a 0.03 positive correlation. However, when changing to Spearman (more robust), the correlation drops to 0, indicating no relationship. For the Sharpe ratio, I find the opposite results: a negative correlation of -0.035 for Pearson, which strengthens to -0.04 when using Spearman. These numbers may seem small to anyone new to finance, but trust me—you get used to it after a while. The signal-to-noise ratio is very low.</p>

<h4 id="portfolio-bucketing"><strong>Portfolio Bucketing</strong></h4>

<p>Next, I mapped each stock’s volatility score to a uniform <strong>0 to 1</strong> distribution and categorized them into one of five portfolios based on their volatility rankings:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Portfolio 1</strong>: Lowest 10% of stocks (low volatility)</li>
  <li><strong>Portfolio 2</strong>: 10% to 20% of stocks</li>
  <li><strong>Portfolio 3</strong>: 20% to 80% of stocks</li>
  <li><strong>Portfolio 4</strong>: 80% to 90% of stocks</li>
  <li><strong>Portfolio 5</strong>: Highest 10% of stocks (high volatility)</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="rebalancing"><strong>Rebalancing</strong></h4>

<p>The portfolios are rebalanced <strong>weekly</strong> to reflect changes in volatility over time. For simplicity, I haven’t factored in transaction costs in this analysis.</p>

<h3 id="constructing-a-long-only-and-long-short-portfolio"><strong>Constructing a Long-Only and Long-Short Portfolio</strong></h3>

<p>Once the stocks are bucketed, I created two types of portfolios: <strong>equal-weighted</strong> and <strong>volatility-targeted</strong>.</p>

<h4 id="1-equal-weighted-portfolio"><strong>1. Equal-Weighted Portfolio</strong></h4>

<p>In the <strong>equal-weighted portfolio</strong>, all stocks are given equal weight, and I remain fully invested at all times. However, this creates a mismatch between the volatilities of the long and short positions, which I’ll explain further below. To construct the long-short portfolio, I simply take the difference between the low-volatility and high-volatility portfolios.</p>

<h4 id="2-volatility-targeted-portfolio"><strong>2. Volatility-Targeted Portfolio</strong></h4>

<p><strong>Volatility targeting</strong> adjusts the weight of each stock based on its volatility to stabilize the portfolio. Here’s how it works:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Target Volatility</strong>: Set a target volatility of 20% annualized.</li>
  <li><strong>Compute Volatility Ratio</strong>: For each stock, calculate:
\(\text{vol_ratio} = \frac{\text{vol_target}}{\text{vol_estimated}}\)
where:
    <ul>
      <li>$\text{vol_target} = 20\%$</li>
      <li>$\text{vol_estimated}$ is the stock’s historical volatility.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Adjust Equal Weights</strong>: Multiply the equal weight of each stock by its $\text{vol_ratio}$:
\(w_i = \text{equal_weight} \times \text{vol_ratio}\)</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Cap Individual Weights</strong>: Ensure no stock weight exceeds 0.05.</li>
  <li><strong>Portfolio Weight Constraint</strong>: Ensure that the portfolio weights total 1. In periods of high volatility, the total weight may be reduced to limit exposure. While this may seem like market timing, I view it more as <strong>dynamically adjusting risk</strong>—a technique commonly used in <strong>Trend following</strong> strategies.</li>
</ol>

<p>The resulting portfolio balances the long and short legs by dynamically adjusting stock weights to achieve the target volatility.</p>

<h3 id="performance-analysis"><strong>Performance Analysis</strong></h3>

<h4 id="equal-weighted-portfolio"><strong>Equal-Weighted Portfolio</strong></h4>

<p>The performance of the equal-weighted long-short portfolio is summarized below. The metrics visualized include return, volatility, and Sharpe ratio—all annualized. Interestingly, the return in the low-volatility portfolio is significantly higher than in the high-volatility portfolio. As expected, the lowest-volatility stocks exhibit the lowest volatility, while the highest-volatility stocks show the highest volatility. Consequently, the low-volatility portfolio exhibits significantly better <strong>risk-adjusted performance</strong>. However, the mismatch between the low-volatility and high-volatility portfolios results in less-than-optimal performance for the long-short portfolio.</p>

<p><strong>Metrics Before Volatility Targeting</strong>:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/2024-12-15-low-volatility-factor/barplot_metrics_ew.svg" alt="Figure 3" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 3</strong>: Bar chart showing Geometric Return, Volatility, and Sharpe Ratio for equal-weighted portfolios (before volatility targeting).</p>

<h3 id="improving-performance-with-volatility-targeting"><strong>Improving Performance with Volatility Targeting</strong></h3>

<p>As shown in the previous figure, volatility targeting adjusts weights to balance risk between the long and short legs, resulting in more stable performance. After applying volatility targeting, we see that the volatility is much more stable across the portfolios. This adjustment improves the <strong>Sharpe ratio</strong> for both the long-short portfolio and the long-only portfolios. The figure below demonstrates the improvement.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/2024-12-15-low-volatility-factor/barplot_metrics_ew_vt.svg" alt="Figure 4" /></p>

<h4 id="metrics-after-volatility-targeting"><strong>Metrics After Volatility Targeting</strong>:</h4>

<p><img src="/assets/2024-12-15-low-volatility-factor/perf_backtest_ew_vt.png" alt="Figure 5" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 5</strong>: Net Asset Value of the volatility-targeted portfolio (after volatility targeting).</p>

<p>Here in Figure 6 below, I visualize the portfolio weights of the long (low volatility, 1) portfolio and the short (high volatility, 5) portfolio. Clearly, the portfolio weight for the high-volatility portfolio is substantially lower. It fluctuates between 0.2 and 0.6, while the portfolio weights for the low-volatility portfolio are almost always close to being fully invested. Only during significant events like the 2000 dot-com bubble, 2009, and the more recent COVID crisis do we see a sudden drop in portfolio weights due to higher volatility.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/2024-12-15-low-volatility-factor/portfolio_weights_long_short_vol_target.svg" alt="Figure 6" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 6</strong>: Portfolio weights for Long and Short portfolios after volatility targeting.</p>

<h3 id="key-takeaways"><strong>Key Takeaways</strong></h3>

<ol>
  <li>A short-term low-volatility factor has historically delivered strong <strong>risk-adjusted returns</strong> (before transaction costs).</li>
  <li>Equal weighting in long-short portfolios leads to volatility imbalances, resulting in suboptimal performance.</li>
  <li>Incorporating a simple volatility-targeting approach effectively balances risk between long and short positions, significantly improving portfolio stability and performance.</li>
</ol>

<p>By incorporating a simple volatility-targeting approach, one can create a more robust and high-performing long-short portfolio. In the next blog, I’ll explore how to combine multiple factors in a portfolio.</p>]]></content><author><name>GitHub User</name><email>your-email@domain.com</email></author><category term="Quant" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The low-volatility factor is a well-known and widely researched concept in factor investing. Simply put, it focuses on selecting stocks with smaller price swings. These more stable, often “boring” stocks tend to outperform their more volatile counterparts on a risk-adjusted basis. Now, you might be thinking—doesn’t higher risk always mean higher returns? Well, as with most things in life, not always. In this post, I’ll take a look at whether the conventional belief about risk and return still holds true.]]></summary></entry></feed>